# Helen Xu

1 Cyclotron Rd, B59-4024J
Berkeley, CA 94704

→ +1 (914) 462 7260

→ hjxu@lbl.gov

→ people.csail.mit.edu/hjxu
Google Scholar: https://bit.ly/3vTLj7o

## Research Vision and Interests

My research vision is to make design, analysis, and usage of parallel and cache-friendly algorithms and data structures as easy as serial computing in a flat memory. My research creates theoretically- and practically-efficient parallel algorithms by using a *locality-first strategy* of first understanding and exploiting locality before introducing parallelism. One example of the locality-first strategy is my work in parallel cache-friendly data structures for **sparse graph and sparse tensor applications** (HPEC '18, IPDPS '18, ALENEX '21, SIGMOD '21).

## **Current Position**

Mar 2022 - Grace Hopper Postdoctoral Scholar in Computing Sciences, Lawrence Berkeley

Present National Laboratory.
Host: Dr. Aydın Buluc

#### Education

Feb 2022 **Ph.D. in Computer Science**, Massachusetts Institute of Technology.

Thesis: The Locality-First Strategy for Developing Efficient Multicore Algorithms

Advisor: Prof. Charles E. Leiserson

May 2018 S.M. in Computer Science, Massachusetts Institute of Technology.

Thesis: Fill Estimation for Blocked Sparse Matrices and Tensors

Advisor: Prof. Charles E. Leiserson

May 2016 B.S. with Honors in Computer Science, Stony Brook University.

Thesis: Write-optimized Skip Lists Advisor: Prof. Michael A. Bender

Awards: Ranked first in the 2016 graduating class of over 100 students and received the

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant Award (top 1% of TAs in the CS department)

## **Publications**

Published 13 peer-reviewed conference papers (9 full papers and 4 short papers) in venues including SIGMOD, PODS, SPAA, and IPDPS.

## Conference Publications

ESA '22 Arghya Bhattacharya, Abiyaz Chowdhury, **Helen Xu**, Rathish Das, Rezaul A. Chowdhury, Rob Johnson, Rishab Nithyanand, Michael A. Bender. "When Are Cache-Oblivious Algorithms Cache Adaptive? A Case Study of Matrix Multiplication and Sorting." In European Symposium on Algorithms, 2022.

- ACDA '21 **Helen Xu**, Sean Fraser, and Charles E. Leiserson. "Multidimensional Included and Excluded Sums." In SIAM Conference on Applied and Computational Discrete Algorithms, 2021.
- SIGMOD '21 Prashant Pandey, Brian Wheatman, **Helen Xu**, and Aydın Buluç. "Terrace: A Hierarchical Graph Container for Skewed Dynamic Graphs." In ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, 2021.
- ALENEX '21 Brian Wheatman and **Helen Xu**. "A Parallel Packed Memory Array for Storing Dynamic Graphs." In SIAM Symposium on Algorithm Engineering and Experiments, 2021.
- APOCS '21 (in alphabetical order) Shahin Kamali and **Helen Xu**. "Beyond Worst-case Analysis of Multicore Caching Strategies." In SIAM Symposium on Algorithmic Principles of Computer Systems, 2021.
  - SPAA '20 (in alphabetical order) Michael A. Bender, Rezaul Chowdhury, Rathish Das, Rob Johnson, William Kuszmaul, Andrea Lincoln, Quanquan C. Liu, Jayson Lynch, and **Helen Xu**. "Closing the Gap Between Cache-Oblivious and Cache-Adaptive Analysis." In ACM Symposium on Parallelism in Algorithms and Architectures, 2020.
  - SPAA '18 (in alphabetical order) Andrea Lincoln, Quanquan C. Liu, Jayson Lynch, and **Helen Xu**. "Cache-Adaptive Exploration: Experimental Results and Scan-Hiding for Adaptivity." In ACM Symposium on Parallelism in Algorithms and Architectures, 2018.
- IPDPS '18 Peter Ahrens, **Helen Xu**, and Nicholas Schiefer. "A Fill Estimation Algorithm for Sparse Matrices and Tensors in Blocked Formats." In IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium, 2018.
- PODS '17 (in alphabetical order) Michael A. Bender, Martin Farach-Colton, Rob Johnson, Simon Mauras, Tyler Mayer, Cynthia Phillips, and **Helen Xu**. "Write-Optimized Skip Lists." In ACM Symposium on Principles of Database Systems, 2017.

#### Peer-Reviewed Short Publications

- HPEC '20 Sean Fraser, **Helen Xu**, and Charles E. Leiserson. "Work-Efficient Parallel Algorithms for Accurate Floating-Point Prefix Sums." In IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conference, 2020.
- SPAA '20 (in alphabetical order) Shahin Kamali and **Helen Xu**. "Brief Announcement: Multicore Paging Algorithms Cannot Be Competitive." In ACM Symposium on Parallelism in Algorithms in Architectures, 2020.
- ICONS '19 (in alphabetical order) James Aimone, Ojas Parekh, Cynthia Phillips, Ali Pinar, William Severa, and **Helen Xu**. "Dynamic Programming with Spiking Neural Computing." In International Conference on Neuromorphic Systems, 2019.
- HPEC '18 Brian Wheatman and **Helen Xu**. "Packed Compressed Sparse Row: A Dynamic Graph Representation." In IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conference, 2018.

**Awards** 

Postdoctoral

- 2022 **Grace Hopper Fellowship in Computing Sciences** for two years of postdoctoral study at Berkeley Lab.
- 2022 **Argonne Training Program for Extreme-Scale Computing (ATPESC)**, a fully-funded two-week course on high-performance computing.

#### Graduate

- 2021 Finalist for Best Student Presentation at ACDA 2021.
- 2020 **Rising Stars Workshop** held virtually at UC Berkeley.
- 2020 **Chateubriand Fellowship** for Spring 2020 at ENS Lyon.
- 2016 National Physical Science Consortium (NPSC) Graduate Fellowship, awarded for six years of graduate study.

## Undergraduate

- 2016 **Undergraduate Teaching Assistant Award,** awarded to around 1% of TAs in the department of Computer Science.
- 2015 **NSF Research Experience for Undergraduates Supplement,** awarded for one year of undergraduate research.
- 2013-2016 **Christian Mata Scholarship for Excellence in Computer Science,** awarded to the top ranked computer science student in every year at Stony Brook University.

## Research Positions Held

- Sep 2016 Supertech Group Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA.
- Feb 2022 Designed, analyzed, and implemented parallel and cache-friendly algorithms for shared-memory multicores.
  - Mentor: Prof. Charles E. Leiserson.
- Summer 2020 **Architecture Research Group** *NVIDIA Research*, Westford, MA.

  Created and evaluated compressed data structures for sparse tensor computations.

  Mentor: Dr. Michael Pellauer.
  - Spring 2020 Resource Optimization: Models, Algorithms, and Scheduling Group ENS Lyon, Lyon, France.

    Studied algorithms for multi-resource job scheduling with theoretical guarantees.

    Mentors: Professors Loris Marchal, Frederic Vivien, and Anne Benoit.
- Summer 2019 **Systems and Networking Group** *Microsoft Research*, Cambridge, UK.

  Developed and implemented algorithms for novel parallel machine learning accelerators.

  Mentor: Dr. Nuno Lopes.
- Summer 2016 **Discrete Mathematics and Optimization Group** Sandia National Laboratories, Albuquerque, NM.

Simplified and refined randomized I/O-efficient data structures.

Mentor: Dr. Cindy Phillips

Summer 2015 **Systems and Security Research Group** *Sandia National Laboratories*, Livermore, CA.

Designed and implemented a network event tracking database using an existing write-optimized fractal tree index.

Mentor: Dr. Tom Kroeger

## **Teaching**

#### Qualifications

2021 Kaufman Teaching Certificate Program (KTCP) Teaching and Learning Lab, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA.

Course page: https://tll.mit.edu/programming/grad-student-programming/kaufman-teaching-certificate-program/

- Completed a semester-long course consisting of developing teaching skills via weekly workshops.
- Prepared and delivered a teaching demo on algorithms to a general audience and provided peer feedback.

## Experience

2017 - 2018 **Teaching Assistant** Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA.

Performance Engineering of Software Systems (6.172, Fall 2017 and Fall 2018) Course page: https://learning-modules.mit.edu/materials/index.html?uuid=/course/6/fa18/6.172

- Led weekly recitations (TA-led tutorial sessions) and office hours.
- Developed the course cloud infrastructure, including the course development environment and tools suite.
- Coordinated with instructors to write and grade homeworks and exams.
- Helped students with assignments on the course discussion forum.
- 2014 2015 **Teaching Assistant** Department of Computer Science, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY.

Foundations of Computer Science (CSE 150, Fall 2014; CSE 215, Spring 2015)

- Led weekly recitations and office hours.
- Coordinated with instructors to write and grade homeworks and exams.

## Students Advised

## PhD

2019-present **Brian Wheatman**, Johns Hopkins University (hosted at Berkeley Lab in Summer 2022).

Compressed Dynamic Data Structures for Efficient Graph Processing.

2020-present Arghya Bhattacharya, Stony Brook University.

An Experimental Evaluation of Cache-Adaptive Algorithms.

M.Eng (graduation dates listed)

expected Feb Amanda Li, MIT.

2023 Efficient Dynamic Graph Processing via Data Structure Design.

June 2020 Sean Fraser, MIT.

Optimizing Parallel Prefix Sums for Scientific Computing.

June 2019 Brian Wheatman, MIT (co-advised with Tim Kaler).

Image Alignment and Dynamic Graph Analytics : Two Case Studies of How Managing Data Movement Can Make (Parallel) Code Run Fast.

June 2019 Stephanie Ren, MIT (co-advised with Tao B. Schardl).

Vector-Aware Space Cuts in Stencil Computations.

## Technical Talks and Presentations

## **Invited Seminars**

## Optimizing Dynamic Graph Processing on Multicores with the Locality-First Strategy

• Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, 2022.

The Locality-First Strategy for Developing Efficient Multicore Algorithms
• MIT, 2021.

## **Data Structure Design for Skewed Dynamic Graphs**

- o MIT Fast Code Seminar, 2021.
- o Williams CS Colloqium, 2021.

## **Updatable Data Compression Formats for Hierarchical Fiber Abstraction**• NVIDIA Research, 2020.

## A Fill-Estimation Algorithm for Sparse Matrices and Tensors in Blocked Formats

o Tel Aviv University, 2019.

#### Conference Talks

#### Multidimensional Included and Excluded Sums

• Finalist for Best Student Presentation at ACDA, 2021.

## Beyond Worst-case Analysis of Multicore Caching Strategies

o APOCS, 2021.

Work-Efficient Parallel Algorithms for Accurate Floating-Point Prefix Sums • HPEC, 2020.

## Multicore Paging Algorithms Cannot Be Competitive

o SPAA, 2020.

## Dynamic Time Warping in Strongly Subquadratic Time: Algorithms for the Low-Distance Regime and Approximate Evaluation

o ICALP, 2019 (filling in for Bill Kuszmaul).

# Cache-Adaptive Exploration: Experimental Results and Scan-Hiding for Adaptivity

o SPAA, 2018.

#### Write-Optimized Skip Lists

- o PODS, 2017 (Joint talk with Tyler Mayer).
- Guest lecture in MIT's advanced performance engineering course (MIT 6.S898), 2017.

#### **Posters**

## A Parallel Packed Memory Array for Dynamic Graphs

o Rising Stars Poster Session, 2020.

## A Fill-Estimation Algorithm for Sparse Matrices and Tensors in Blocked Formats

CSAIL Alliances Poster Session, 2018.

## Performance Engineering Discussions

## Software Performance Engineering at the End of Moore's Law

Jane Street Symposium, 2020.

#### Leiserchess Codewalk

o Guest lecture in Performance Engineering of Software Systems (MIT 6.172), 2018.

## Professional Service

Program Committee, ALENEX (2022, 2023), SPAA (2022).

(Sub)Reviewer, JPDC (2022), ICPP (2021), ACDA (2021), WADS (2021), SPAA (2021, 2020), EuroPar (2020), SOSA (2020), SODA (2019, 2018), ESA (2019, 2022).

## **Outreach Activities**

2018 - 2022 **Communication Lab Advisor** with the MIT Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Communications Lab.

Communication Lab Page: http://mitcommlab.mit.edu/eecs/

- Reviewed over 50 papers, talks, statements, and CVs via peer coaching.
- Created and implemented a partnership with Professor Saman Amarasinghe's research group to jointly prepare conference presentations via weekly meetings.
- Prepared and led workshops for the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship application (2020, 2021) and the PhD research qualifying exam presentation (2019, 2021).
- Wrote articles about core technical communications topics, such as thesis proposals and paper abstracts.
- 2017 Co-president of MIT Graduate Women in Course 6 (GW6).

Webpage: http://gw6.scripts.mit.edu/

 Organized events several times per month for graduate women in the department, including professional development and social activities.

## References

## Prof. Charles E. Leiserson

Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science
Massachusetts Institute of Technology cel@mit.edu
+1 (617) 642-6521

## Prof. Shahin Kamali

Department of Computer Science York University kamalis@yorku.ca +1 (416) 736-2100

## Prof. Michael A. Bender

Department of Computer Science Stony Brook University bender@cs.stonybrook.edu +1 (631) 987-8035

## Dr. Aydın Buluç

Computational Research Division Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratories abuluc@lbl.gov +1 (510) 325-9659